# Charles C. Lanfear Curriculum Vitae

April 20, 2022

### Personal Summary

I am a Postdoctoral Researcher at the Centre for Social Investigation and a Research Fellow of Nuffield College in the University of Oxford. I conduct theory-driven research on the ways communities respond to crime and the consequences of those responses using methods from demography, computational social science, and causal inference.

- Centre for Social Investigation,
   Nuffield College,
   University of Oxford
- clanfear.github.io
- Clanfear
- **y** @cclanfear

### **Professional Appointments**

University Assistant Professor (Beginning Sep. 2022) Institute of Criminology, University of Cambridge

Postdoctoral Researcher

Center for Social Investigation, Nuffield College, University of Oxford

Research Fellow

Nuffield College, University of Oxford

#### Education

2021	PhD in Sociology — University of Washington Dissertation: Integrating Collective Efficacy and Criminal Opportunity: Disorder, the Built Environment, and Policing
2017	Master of Arts in Sociology — University of Washington Thesis: Disorder in the Neighborhood: A Large-Scale Field Experiment on Disorder, Norm Violation, and Pro-Social Behavior
2013	Master of Public Policy — Oregon State University Thesis: Exploring a Mental Health Crisis: An Examination of Mental Health Arrests in Benton County, OR

#### **Publications**

CC Lanfear. 2022. Collective Efficacy and the Built Environment. Criminology 60(2)

**CC Lanfear**, RL Matsueda, LR Beach. 2020. Broken Windows, Informal Social Control, and Crime: Assessing Causality in Empirical Studies. *Annual Review of Criminology* 3

RL Matsueda, **CC Lanfear**. 2020. Differential Association Theory. *Wiley Blackwell Encyclopedia of Sociology, 2nd Ed.* 

RL Matsueda, **CC Lanfear**. 2020. Collective Action, Rational Choice, and Gang Delinquency: Appreciating Short and Strodtbeck (1965). *Social Bridges and Contexts in Criminology and Sociology: Reflections on the Intellectual Legacy of James F. Short, Jr.* 

**CC Lanfear**, LR Beach, TA Thomas. 2018. Formal Social Control in Changing Neighborhoods: Racial Implications of Neighborhood Context on Reactive Policing. *City & Community* 17(4)

BC Burkhardt, SM Akins, J Sassaman, S Jackson, K Elwer, **CC Lanfear**, M Amorim, KM Stevens. 2017. University Researcher and Law Enforcement Collaboration: Lessons from a Study of Justice-Involved Persons with Suspected Mental Illness. *International Journal of Offender Therapy and Comparative Criminology* 61(5)

SM Akins, BC Burkhardt, **CC Lanfear**. 2016. Law Enforcement Response to "Frequent Fliers" An Examination of High-Frequency Contacts Between Police and Justice-Involved Persons With Mental Illness. *Criminal Justice Policy Review* 27(1)

**CC Lanfear**, SM Akins, CJ Mosher. 2013. Examining the Relationship of Substance Use and Sexual Orientation. *Deviant Behavior* 34(7)

SM Akins, **CC Lanfear**, S Cline, CJ Mosher. 2013. Patterns and Correlates of Adult American Indian Substance Use. *Journal of Drug Issues* 43(4)

### Policy Reports

CC Lanfear. 2019. Terry Stop Bias Report. Seattle Police Department

RD Crutchfield, A Harris, **CC Lanfear**, TA Thomas. 2017. UWPD Racial Bias in Contacts Analysis. *Office of the University of Washington President* 

**CC Lanfear**. 2014. 2013 County Jail Survey Executive Summary. *Association of Oregon Community Mental Health Programs* 

SM Akins, BC Burkhardt, **CC Lanfear**, KM Stevens, M Amorim. 2013. Law Enforcement Response to People with Mental Illnesses in Benton County. *Benton County Sheriff's Office and the Willamette Criminal Justice Commission* 

#### Presentations

Nov 16, 2020	Property Crime, Fear of Crime, and Social Control of Homelessness in Seattle. American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting, Washington D.C. (Canceled due to COVID-19)
Nov 14, 2019	Disorder and Social Control: Experimental Evidence on Prosocial and Antisocial Behavior. <i>American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting</i> , San Francisco, CA
Sep 27, 2019	Searching for the Center (with SM Karceski). SocSem, University of Washington
Jan 16, 2019	Complaints and the Social Control of Homelessness in Seattle. <i>SocSem</i> , University of Washington
Oct 26, 2018	Disorder and Social Control. SocSem, University of Washington
Nov 16, 2016	Disorder in the Neighborhood: A Large-Scale Field Experiment on Disorder, Norm Violation, and Pro-Social Behavior. <i>American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting</i> , New Orleans, LA
Aug 21, 2016	Formal Social Control in Changing Seattle Neighborhoods. <i>American Sociological Association Annual Meeting</i> , Seattle, WA
Aug 20, 2016	Racial and Social Control in Changing Neighborhoods: Who Complains to the Police and Why It Matters. <i>Society for the Study of Social Problems Annual Meeting</i> , Seattle, WA
Nov 20, 2014	Frequent Flyers and Civil Commitment: Repeat Police Contacts with Mentally Ill Suspects. <i>American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting</i> , San Francisco, CA
Jan 22, 2014	Police Contacts with People with Mental Illness in Benton County. <i>Willamette Criminal Justice Commission</i> , Corvallis, OR

# Courses (Instructor)

2017 – 2021	Introduction to R for Social Scientists (CSSS508) University of Washington - 9 terms
2020 – 2021	Criminology (SOC371) University of Washington - 2 terms
2017	Introduction to Social Statistics (SOC221) University of Washington - 1 term

### Invited Talks

May 31, 2019	Reproducibility: Organization, Tools, and Best Practices
	Center for Studies in Demography and Ecology Professionalization Seminar,
	University of Washington
Oct 25, 2018	Research Practices: Organization, Tools, and Reproducibility
	Built Environments PhD Seminar, University of Washington

### Grants and Awards

2021 — Present	Research Fellowship, Nuffield College, University of Oxford
2020	Excellence in Teaching Award, University of Washington
2018	Distinguished Master's Thesis Award - Social Sciences, University of Washington
2018 - 2019	Best Graduate Instructor, Sociology Department, University of Washington
2017 — 2018	Outstanding Performance for the Master of Arts, Sociology Department, University of Washington
2017	CSDE Lightning Talk and Poster Session - Best Poster, Center for Studies in Demography and Ecology, University of Washington
2014	Blalock Fellowship, Center for Statistics and the Social Sciences, University of Washington
2012 - 2013	Oregon Lottery Graduate Scholarship, Oregon State University
2011 - 2012	Laurels Graduate Scholarship, Oregon State University

### Service

2019	Faculty Search Committee (2 searches), Sociology Department, University of
	Washington
2019 - 2020	Undergraduate Thesis Co-Advisor: Peter Novello, University of Washington
2018 - 2019	Graduate Student Assoc. President, Sociology Department, University of Washington
2016 - 2017	Associate Student Editor, Social Problems
2015 – 2018	Graduate Student Assoc. Representative to CS&SS, Sociology Department, University of Washington

## Media Coverage

Jan 24, 2022	Homeless camps are often blamed for crime but experts say it's not so simple. NPR
Apr 3, 2021	Tents in Seattle increased by more than 50% after COVID pandemic began, survey says. <i>The Seattle Times</i>
	says. The Seattle Times
Oct 11, 2016	UW study seems to equate Black Lives Matter and Nazis?. Crosscut

Apr 7, 2016	A new method for identifying those with mental illness who have frequent contacts	
	with police may help those in need to get treatment. London School of Economics US	
	Centre	
Feb 16, 2015	Study aims to help ID mental health issues that take up police time. <i>KMTR News Source</i> 16	

# Selected Work Experience

Apr 2022 – Present	Associate Department of Sociology, Harvard University
Jan 2015 – Jun 2021	Graduate Research Assistant University of Washington
Jan 2020 – Mar 2020	Graduate Student Consultant University of Washington – Center for Social Science Computation and Research
Jan 2019 — Mar 2019	Graduate Student Consultant University of Washington – Center for Social Science Computation and Research
Jun 2019 – Dec 2019	Research Consultant Seattle Police Department
Mar 2018 – Jun 2018	Graduate Student Consultant University of Washington – Center for Social Science Computation and Research
Apr 2016 – Sep 2017	Research Consultant University of Washington – Office of the President
Jul 2014 – Dec 2014	Social Science Computing and Statistical Analyst University of Washington
Jan 2013 – Jun 2013	Research Intern Benton County Sheriff's Office, Corvallis, OR
Sep 2011 – Jun 2013	Graduate Research Assistant Oregon State University

## Reviews

American Journal of Sociology Criminology International Migration Review Journal of Research in Crime and Delinquency Justice Quarterly